Silver Lion Venice International Film Festival 1953
Daiei Productions Presents
UGETSU MONOGATARI
Produced by NAGATA Masaichi
From Ugetsu monogatari by Ueda Akinari
Screenplay by KAWAGUCHI Matsutaro YODA Yoshikata
Cinematography by MIYAGAWA Kazuo
Art Direction by ITO Kisaku Music by HAYASAKA Fumio
Cast
KYO Machiko as Lady Wakasa , MITO Mitsuko as Ohama
TANAKA Kinuyo as Miyagi
MORO Masayuki as Genjuro , OZAWA Sakae as Tobei
AOYAMA Sugisaku as the Priest
KAGAWA Ryosuke as the Village Chief , MORI Kikue as Lady Wakasa 's Nurse
AMANO Ichiro as the Boatman , SAWAMURA Ikio as Genichi
Directed by MIZOGUCHI Kenji
Ugetsu monogatari by Ueda Akinari
continues to enchant modern readers with its mysterious fantasies .
This film is a new refashioning of those fantasies .
Early Spring , 16th Century The Age of Civil Wars
North shores of Lake Biwa in Omi Province
What could that be ?
They must be executing Shibata 's spies .
I need to sell all this before the fighting starts .
Can you sell it in Nagahama ?
I hear business is booming there since Lord Hashiba 's forces arrived .
- Can 't I go with you ? - No , no women .
There 's no telling what lawless soldiers will get up to .
Besides , you have to stay and take care of little Genichi .
Go , then , if that 's what you want ! Some samurai you 'll make , you fool !
How high can a man rise without big dreams ?
Ambition must be as boundless as the ocean .
You must be dreaming ! You can 't even handle a sword .
You should stick to the trade you know or you 'll regret it .
Just wait until I 'm rich .
I swear by the god of war , I 'm tired of being poor .
Genjuro , please take me with you .
Still at it ? Forget your foolish dreams .
- Let me pull the cart . - Stop it , you fool !
He 's delusional , he thinks a big future awaits him in Nagahama .
What an idiot !
Back soon , Miyagi .
They 're too greedy for their own good . And not just Tobei . Genjuro , too .
I tell you , quick profits made in chaotic times never last .
A little money inflames men 's greed .
They 'd do better to prepare for the coming war .
- Tell Genjuro that when he returns . - I shall .
Thank you for your advice .
Your father 's back !
Welcome back .
Here ...
Look !
- What 's this ? - What do you think ?
You got that for your wares ?
Feel the weight of it .
Never seen so much , have you ? I hurried back just to show you .
That 's what I call trade ! Now do you understand ?
What about Tobei ?
He came across a fine-looking samurai in Nagahama .
I tried to stop him , but he insisted on following the samurai .
I beg of you , sir ! I beg of you !
Please , I beg of you , sir !
Let me be your vassal ! I 'll serve you unto death , sir !
- Accept a beggar as a vassal ? - Get some armour first !
- Armour and a spear ! - Get lost , beggar !
Then can I be a samurai ?
Get lost !
Not you again ?
Get some armour and a spear !
You look so nice ! Happy now ?
Very smart indeed .
It 's like the Bon festival and New Year 's all rolled into one .
For years I 've wanted to buy you a kimono but I could never afford it .
Now I finally can !
Just look at your face . You look so happy !
It 's not the kimono but your kindness that makes me so happy .
As long as you 're with me , I want for nothing in life .
Just look at all this ...
Dried fish , oil , flour , arrowroot and rice cakes .
Money is everything , see ?
Without it life is hard ,
and all hope dies .
Well , your father 's got work to do .
Up we go .
I will earn even more .
I 'll try and make as much pottery as I can .
That last small batch brought in three silver coins .
That 's enough talk of money . We have plenty now .
The village chief says Lord Shibata 's troops could be here by tomorrow .
We should be careful ...
Nonsense !
War 's always good for business . Just look how much I made !
You were fortunate once . You may not be next time .
- If anything happened to you ... - Stop imagining the worst .
Oh , Ohama ...
- Brother ... - You mustn 't worry .
No samurai would hire a peasant dressed in rags like him .
Don 't you worry , he 'll be back .
Have something to drink , here .
You fool !
Have you come to your senses ?
You look like a beggar .
You 've become the village idiot !
Keep it turning , come on .
Get him out of here ! He 's in the way .
We won 't make it if we don 't hurry .
Stay out of the way , now . Go and sit down .
Mother , I 'm hungry .
What a pest !
Come on , come on , a few more turns !
You 're a different man now ,
always so irritable .
All I want is for us to work in peace as husband and wife ,
and for the three of us to live happily .
That 's all I wish for .
You really worked hard for me this time .
I have a plan , that 's why .
Let 's sell this new batch in Nagahama . We 'll make a fortune .
- Will I get a share ? - Of course . A third of all we sell .
I can 't wait ... I can 't wait to get my hands on that money .
I 've never seen those two work so hard before .
They 've thrown everything into this kiln ,
their strength , their souls , everything .
I don 't know what will become of them if it all fails .
Living together as a happy family is enough for me .
But he insists on taking this risk . Men just won 't listen , will they ?
Genjuro was always so level-headed before .
War changes people , doesn 't it ?
At least they 're trying to bring in some money .
I wonder what that is .
Wake up , dear . Wake up .
The rumour was true . They must be Shibata 's troops .
See anything , Tobei ?
The villagers are scattering like spiders !
- What now ? - We must keep the kiln burning .
I 'll be damned if I let that fire go out .
They 're pillaging houses and rounding up men .
Genichi !
It 's Shibata 's army ! Hurry , run !
Hurry , hurry !
Hurry !
Halt ! We 're taking men for forced labour ! Don 't try to resist !
This is terrible ! Run for your lives ! Lord Shibata 's troops are here !
They 're stealing everything ! Hide your valuables !
- Don 't let them get your women ! - Hurry !
They 're taking all men into forced labour !
- They 're requisitioning everything ! - They 're like a pack of wolves .
If only they 'd waited one more night !
Hurry , let 's run . It 's too dangerous here . Hurry !
If we lose this batch , I won 't get my share of the profits !
You 'll lose your life for that kiln ! Come on !
Come now , quickly !
Boil some rice . We 'll need it in the mountains .
Ohama ! Ohama , come quickly !
Mother !
Trying to hide , eh ? Come out , damn you !
Help ! Please ! Help !
Please have mercy ! Don 't take them ! Don 't leave us to starve !
We 're begging you !
No , please ! No !
Out of my way !
Out of the way , fool !
Help !
It 's ready . Here ...
Thank you .
Hurry and eat .
- What 's happened to him ? - Hopeless fool !
- Have you seen my husband ? - No , I haven 't .
Who 's there ?
It 's really quietened down .
The guns are almost silent .
Where are you going ?
It 's too dangerous . Wait until the soldiers leave .
Wait . It 's best to wait .
I can 't wait ! I have to go !
- Please don 't go ! - I can 't let the fire go out !
Forget the kiln ! What if you 're caught ?
- I can 't let the fire go out ! - We can always make more pots .
Silence ! I can 't let the pots be ruined .
Ohama ! Ohama !
Damn it ! The fire 's gone out .
- Dear ... - Too late . The fire 's gone out .
Damn , it 's empty !
- What was that ? Is someone hiding ? - Could be something hidden in there .
Have a look .
Nothing but pots .
Let 's go .
They 're done !
Look ! They 're fired !
Thank goodness they 're done !
They 're done !
Thank goodness .
Are they done ?
Yes , they are ! And very nicely , too .
- Hurry and load them up . - So we 're off to Nagahama , then ?
We can 't now . We 'll row across the lake .
Ohama 's a boatman 's daughter . You do the rowing , okay ?
- Can we get to the lake safely ? - We 'll take a shortcut to Onoe .
Will we find a boat ?
There are always abandoned ones there .
Hurry , let 's unload the kiln .
~ In the waters of Azuchi ~
~ A little boat floats along ~
~ All are asleep ~
~ Slumped over the rudder ... ~
We 've got to be careful , the fog is thick .
Genichi , this is the lake . Isn 't it beautiful ?
We 're finally out of danger .
I 'm glad we decided to go by boat .
If we 'd gone over land , we 'd probably be dead by now .
We 'll reach Omizo by morning .
That 's where Lord Niwa has his castle .
The town 's even more prosperous than Nagahama .
You and I will be rich men ,
and our wives will be wealthy women .
I 'll build a warehouse in our village .
And I 'll buy a suit of armour .
Another boat !
It 's a ghost !
No ... I 'm not a ghost .
I 'm a boatman from Kaizu .
I was on the way to Azuchi with my cargo ,
when I was attacked by pirates .
Water ...
Give me water !
Thank you .
Wherever you 're headed , be on the lookout for pirates .
If they see you ,
you 'll lose your cargo and your lives .
Take care of your women .
Your women ...
Merciful Buddha !
Buddha have mercy on his soul .
Let 's turn back . This is a bad omen .
Let 's return the women to shore . We 'll continue alone .
- Please don 't go . - I 'm staying ... to keep my eye on him .
- They kidnap women . - I 'll risk it .
I 'll go wherever you go . Please take me with you .
- You must look after Genichi . - Take me with you !
Ohama , take us back to shore . Quickly !
Tobei , take us back !
We 'll be back with the money soon .
We 'll return within ten days . Wait for us .
Don 't try to fight if pirates overtake you .
I know , I know . Don 't take the main road .
Remember what I said and take the mountain path .
And don 't go back home right away . Understand ?
These misfortunes will soon be over . Just be patient .
Tobei , Ohama , please look after him for me .
Don 't worry , we 'll be back soon .
Take good care of Genichi .
You 'll be surprised at all the silver we bring back .
Father !
Please be careful !
Come back safely !
- Father ! - Please be careful !
Father !
Buy our wares ! Buy our wares !
Tea bowls ! Tea bowls !
This ? Here you go . Many thanks .
- Sake flasks and cups , too ! - Buy our wares !
- I 'd like that vase , please . - This one , yes ?
And that sake flask and those cups .
And can we also take those rice bowls , plates and jars ?
Yes ... rice bowls , plates and jars .
We live at Kutsuki Manor . Please deliver them there .
We will pay you then .
Thank you .
- The castle guard approaches ! - Make way for the castle guard !
Don 't look ! You 'll only get your crazy ideas again .
Shut up !
If I had armour , I could be a samurai . Sword , spear , armour ...
Don 't throw away our hard-earned money .
- Leave me alone ! - Brother !
- Tobei ! - Let go of me !
Next time we meet , I 'll be a great samurai .
Please stop him !
Tobei ! Tobei !
That got rid of her .
- May I help you ? - A suit of armour , please !
Tobei !
- Do I look like a samurai ? - Yes , and a fine one .
- But you need a spear . - I 'll take one !
Here you are .
How much ?
One silver piece .
Pretty , isn 't she ?
Let me go !
What are you doing ?
Damn you !
Murderers !
There 's some money for you .
Bastards !
Look what 's become of me .
Satisfied now , Tobei , seeing your wife reduced to this ?
What do you care , anyway , now you think you 're a samurai ?
Tobei , you wretched fool !
You fool , Tobei !
Would you watch over my stall until my partners return ?
- Of course . - They should be back soon . Thanks .
Sir , how much is one of these ?
Are you looking to buy ?
Depends on the price .
They 're too luxurious for the wife of a man like you .
I 've got money .
Excuse me .
We thought you might need us to show you the way .
That 's very kind of you .
Please follow us .
Please come in .
Well ... Thank you , but I should be getting back .
Lady Wakasa is waiting for you . Please come inside .
You say " Lady Wakasa " ... Are you referring to the young lady ?
Yes , she is the daughter of the late Lord Kutsuki .
Now please come through . No need to stand on ceremony .
Many thanks .
Come through .
Please ...
Please , come .
You are Master Genjuro of Omi province , are you not ?
How does your ladyship know my name ?
When I saw your ceramics at the market ,
I could hardly believe my eyes .
The blue glaze on your pots gleamed as brightly as crystal .
My father taught me a certain appreciation of such things .
I wanted to meet you ,
to ask how you manage to create such beautiful objects .
But perhaps it is a trade secret , not meant for outsiders ?
No , my lady , there is no special trade secret .
But it takes many years ' experience to handle the clay and apply the glaze .
The fruit of experience is beauty ,
but only a master craftsman can create such beauty .
Thank you , my lady .
These are my wares , aren 't they ?
I wanted to taste sake from your cups .
You 're fortunate , my little ones , to catch this noble lady 's eye .
I 'm a farmer , so the pottery is just a sideline ,
but I feel for my creations , as if they were my own children .
That such a noble lady would look kindly upon them is a great honour .
To see them in such a grand residence ,
graced by the touch of so beautiful a lady ,
is like a dream come true .
Not at all . They must be saddened by the touch
of one fallen on hard times , such as myself .
Please , take a cup .
My wares have never looked so beautiful .
The value of people and objects truly depends on their setting .
My wares must be at a loss to find themselves in such a noble manor .
Your talent must not be hidden away in some poor , remote village .
You must strive to deepen and enrich your gift .
And how might I do that , my lady ?
By swearing your love for Lady Wakasa ,
and pledging your troth to her at once .
~ The finest silk ~
~ Of choicest hue ~
~ May change and fade away ~
~ As would my life ~
~ My beloved ~
~ If thou shouldst prove untrue ~
~ Our vow to Iove for a thousand years ... ~
~ Is sealed with this cup ... ~
His voice sounds overjoyed !
That is the voice of my late father .
The entire House of Kutsuki was wiped out
by Oda Nobunaga , that detestable Oda Nobunaga .
The only survivors of the purge were her ladyship
and myself , her nurse .
But the spirit of the late daimyo lingers in the palace ,
and it sings like this every time her ladyship dances .
Is it not a splendid voice ?
He 's expressing his delight at her ladyship 's impending marriage .
Whenever I hear the voice of my late father ...
It 's too early to rise . Please sleep as long as you like .
What am I doing here ?
What a thing to say
as if you 'd forgotten everything .
Is my lord awake ?
Lead your husband by the hand to the spring and bathe him .
I won 't intrude upon you any further .
You have such a look of distrust on your face .
You think I 'm some kind of enchantress , don 't you ?
But you 're mine , you belong to me now .
From now on , you must devote your entire life to me .
~ This Iove ~
~ This Iove of ours ~
~ Has driven me to madness ... ~
Even if you are a ghost or enchantress ,
I 'll never let you go .
I never imagined such pleasures existed .
This is exquisite ! It 's paradise !
Help me ! Help me !
Somebody , please help !
Someone , help me !
See any food ?
Quickly , quickly !
Pull yourself together . Come with me .
Come quickly !
- Take these rice cakes and this . - I 'll never forget your kindness .
You 'll be all right if you take the back road .
- To the left . - Many thanks .
Be careful .
Here !
It 's mine !
- Hey ... you got any food ? - We 're starving to death .
That food 's for my son . Please don 't take it !
Do me the honour of beheading me .
I 've brought you a head ! A head ! A general 's head !
Please , my lord !
- What is it ? - Please look at this !
You found the head of a great general .
No , I didn 't find it , my lord . I killed him with my spear !
Who 'd believe a warrior like Fuwa Katsuhige
would let a mere foot soldier kill him ?
A lucky find , but you 'll be rewarded all the same .
What would you like ?
A horse , armour and vassals .
Very well . You shall have them .
Thank you , my lord !
You 're a clever one , aren 't you ?
He looks like a fine samurai . What clan does he belong to ?
- He killed Fuwa , the great general . - What 's his name ?
Tobei of Nakanogo , one of Lord Niwa 's top men .
Pay homage , that you may be so lucky .
Beautiful girls are waiting for brave warriors !
We have the finest sake and fish ! Please come inside !
I can 't let you pass , sir !
Come and look . We have beautiful girls inside .
- What 's going on ? - Chief , perhaps we can rest here .
No , I 'm heading directly home .
I have someone waiting for me , and she must see me in all my glory .
Chief , why not let us celebrate your triumph ?
- Your men are looking forward to it . - I see . Very well .
I , Nakanogo Tobei of Lord Niwa 's army , will rest here .
- Prepare some tables . - He 'll rest here . Show your gratitude .
Thank you , sir .
Make way !
Clear the way for Master Tobei !
Welcome .
- Which one is this Tobei ? - Him , over there .
Him ?
I heard of his great exploits .
May I drink from your cup so your luck rubs off on me ?
Me , too !
How did you manage to kill such a great general ?
Yes , tell us , so we may do as you did !
A guide for future action !
There 's nothing much to tell .
First , you need brains . You need knowledge .
Then , a strong arm . Skill on the battlefield .
Martial artistry .
Speed to seize the moment . The ability to see life in perspective .
Then you 'll be wise as Kongming , the great Chinese military strategist .
But above all , keep a clear , discerning mind .
- Got that ? - Indeed .
For military tactics , study the Kusunoki and Koshu schools .
For firearms , Kanamaru school . For the spear , Otsubo school .
Next you need to know fortifications and fortresses .
Then defensive tactics , V-formations and the like ...
Hey ! My money !
Let me go !
Crazy bitch !
- Someone stop him ! - Hey , what 's going on ?
- Let go of me ! - He 's trying to run off like a thief !
I don 't give money to wenches like you .
Scoundrel ! Making a plaything of me .
This will do just fine , thanks !
Ohama ! Ohama !
So you 're the big man now ?
You 've finally become the great samurai of your dreams , eh ?
While you 've made your way to the top , I 've made quite a name for myself .
In my fancy kimono and make-up , drinking fine sake ,
I bed a different man every night .
Some success for a woman , isn 't it ?
Happy now ? This is what you wanted .
Success always comes at a price , and we pay in suffering .
I may be a fallen woman , but your success wipes the slate clean .
Come !
Be my customer tonight and we 'll celebrate .
Buy this fallen woman with your money !
Ohama .
Without you , my success means nothing .
That 's a lie ! My fate meant nothing , as long as you became a samurai .
No , no , no , you 're wrong .
Ohama !
I thought you 'd be proud if I made good .
I never dreamed you 'd be brought to this .
I 'm a defiled woman .
And you 're to blame !
- Can you restore my honour ? - I can .
- Otherwise , I have to die ! - I can !
I swear I 'll restore your honour .
How many times I 've wanted to die ,
but I had to see you first !
I hated myself for it , I hated myself ,
but I couldn 't die without seeing you first !
I couldn 't die ... I couldn 't die !
This
and this . Thank you .
I don 't quite have enough . Could you lower the price ?
In that case , I 'll take this back .
I really wanted that .
Come to Kutsuki Manor and I 'll pay you the rest .
- Kutsuki Manor ? - Yes , at the foot of the mountain .
Take it all ,
and go away !
Keep your money , too . Just go away !
- Wait . - How can I help you , Priest ?
I sense something evil ... an ill omen .
- What is it ? - Let me look closely at your face .
- My face ? - Yes .
We can 't talk here . Please follow me .
Very well ...
The shadow of death is upon your face .
Has some strange apparition crossed your path , perhaps ?
No , not at all .
Have you no home , no family ?
If others depend on you , you must return to them at once .
If you remain here any longer , you will forfeit your life .
Return home quickly .
But why ?
Do not ask the reason . Your life is at stake .
But I spend my days happily with Lady Wakasa at Kutsuki Manor .
- She is a spirit of the dead . - What nonsense .
This love of yours is forbidden .
Do you not love your wife and child ?
Would you forsake your life and abandon them , too ?
Wait !
Go then , if you must ,
but I cannot let you walk into the jaws of death .
I will exorcise this ghost .
Come .
When you realise how terrifying this spirit is ,
you 'll come to your senses .
Oh ... how beautiful !
Such lovely jewellery !
You 've made me so happy !
How thoughtful of you , sir .
I 'm so relieved .
You were so late in returning that I grew terribly worried .
But you look troubled , my dear .
What has happened ?
What is it ?
You must not leave here again .
Since the fall of our clan ,
people have treated us with nothing but contempt
and slander our name .
What a wretched world !
Genjuro ,
I want you never to leave my side again .
Let 's leave this manor and return to my native province .
Genjuro , you are my husband for life .
You will accompany me , won 't you ?
Please forgive me .
I 've been ...
I 've been lying to you .
I have a wife and child .
I left them back home in the chaos of the war .
You must leave all that behind you now .
Please let me go !
No !
I refuse to let you go .
So , you will come with me to my native province
immediately .
What is it , my lady ?
- He has something on his skin ! - His skin ?
Genjuro , did you ... ?
- Did you ... ? - On your skin ?
You must wash away what 's on your skin !
Why did you wed her if you were already married ?
I don 't know ... How could I have made such a terrible mistake ?
A mistake for a man perhaps , but for a woman , it 's far worse .
Please forgive me . Let me go .
Certainly not !
Wipe off those Sanskrit prayers to the Buddha and that curse ,
or we will never forgive you !
Genjuro ,
how could you even think of doing something so dreadful ?
All I wish is to remain forever by your side .
For all eternity .
Lady Wakasa departed this world
without ever having known love in her life .
It grieved my heart to see her so sorrowful .
I wanted her ladyship to enjoy fully the pleasures of a woman 's life ,
so I chose to return with her ,
to wander this world .
Our hopes were fulfilled
when she met a good man like you
and found a love that occurs only once a lifetime .
And now , when she has at last found joy ,
you speak of returning home ,
never to see each other again .
Does it not pain you to know
that you may ruin her ladyship 's only chance of happiness ?
Do you feel no remorse ?
Master Genjuro , you must banish these dreadful thoughts
and stay by her side forever ...
Please forgive me ! Forgive me !
Genjuro !
This is the man !
Hey , you ! Get up !
- What are you doing ? - You shameless thief !
You stole a sacred treasure from the shrine .
- You 're wrong ! I didn 't steal it . - Silence !
This sacred sword disappeared a month ago .
That can 't be ! It belongs to Lady Wakasa at Kutsuki Manor .
- Kutsuki Manor , you say ? - That 's right !
You must 've been dreaming .
This is where it stood before the clan was wiped out .
He 's lying through his teeth !
Where in the manor did you find the sword ?
He 's suspicious . Search him .
That 's my money ! Give it back !
Silence ! In peace time , we 'd throw you in jail ,
but Shibata 's army burned it down .
Be thankful for that , you lucky bastard .
~ The finest silk ~
~ Of choicest hue ~
~ May change and fade away ~
~ As would my life ~
~ My beloved ... ~
Miyagi .
Miyagi !
- I 'm sorry I was gone so long . - You 're back !
I knew you 'd be worried about me . But you 're all right ...
I 'm so happy to see you 're all right .
- Genichi ? - He 's asleep .
Let me hold him , let me hold him .
Genichi ...
Genichi , I 'm back ! I 'm back !
Your father 's returned . Let me hold you , let me hold you ...
I wanted to bring you back fine presents , but this is all I have .
I ... I made a terrible mistake !
Don 't say another word , my dear . You 've returned safely to us .
I realise now how right you were . My mind was warped .
Let 's not speak of it anymore .
You must be exhausted .
I have some sake prepared .
And there 's a stew ready in the pot .
I feel so relieved .
Sake never tasted so good .
It 's so peaceful here .
Come , Genichi . I 'll put you to bed .
I haven 't had a moment 's peace since I left here ,
but I 'm home at last ... home at last ...
Home at last ... home at last ...
Is someone in there ? Open the door !
Is someone in there ? Open up .
- Village chief ! - Genjuro ! You 're back ?
Yes . Thank you for all your kindness in my absence .
Oh , there you are , my boy !
I was worried , I didn 't know where you 'd gone .
What a relief .
The boy must have heard you were back .
Hey , Miyagi ...
Miyagi !
Genjuro ...
Are you dreaming ?
Dreaming ?
Miyagi was killed by soldiers of the defeated army .
Killed ?
She 'd have been so happy to see you back safely .
Poor thing .
Merciful Buddha ...
Ever since Miyagi died ,
I 've been looking after your boy in my house .
I was so afraid when he suddenly disappeared last night .
The bond between parent and child is strong .
But how could he have known that you 'd returned ?
To hell with this ... and this
and this !
I told you so , but you were too stupid to learn except through misfortune .
The war drove us mad with ambition .
Don 't let my suffering be in vain .
Pull yourself together and work hard .
Why did you have to die ?
Miyagi , why did you have to die ?
I did not die .
I am at your side .
Your delusion has come to an end .
You are again your true self , in the place where you belong .
Your work is waiting ...
What a beautiful shape !
Helping you spin the wheel is my greatest pleasure .
How I long to see it when it 's fired .
The firewood is cut and ready .
The rampaging soldiers are gone .
So make your wonderful pottery in peace .
So many things have happened .
You 've finally become the man I had hoped for .
But , alas
I am no longer among the living .
Such is the way of the world .
You must be tired . Rest a while .
Here , Genichi . It 's delicious .
Eat it while it 's hot .
Brother , eat before it gets cold .